A Finding Aid to the Ruth Gikow papers, 1933-1982, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Ruth Gikow papers
1933-1982
Archives of American Art
Gikow, Ruth, 1915-1982
AAA.gikoruth
Archival Resource Key
2 Linear feet
The Ruth Gikow papers measure 2 linear feet and date from 1933-1982. The papers document Gikow's life and career as a figurative painter and illustrator through biographical material; personal and professional correspondence with family, galleries, universities, and colleagues; autobiographical essays and writings on art broadly, lists of artwork and other writings; personal business files such as sale records and price lists; exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and other printed material; and photographs of Gikow and her artwork.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Scope and Contents
The Ruth Gikow papers measure 2 linear feet and date from 1933-1982. The papers document Gikow's life and career as a figurative painter and illustrator through biographical material, correspondence, writings, personal business files, printed material and photographic material. Biographical material contains resumes, Gikows passports, a transcript from a Jewish Home Show radio interview and an audio interview with Gikow done by Karl E. Fortess. Correspondence is between Gikow and her family, critics and galleries, and from colleagues including Karl Fortess and Lee Nordness, and one letter each from Werner Drewes, Jo Hopper, and Raphael Soyer. Writings consists of essays by Gikow on her life and career and on art and artists more broadly. Other writings include an annotated appointment calander, lists of her artwork and miscellaneous notes.
Personal business records document Gikow's career through sale records and price lists, as well as receipts and correspondence related to the production of a catalog of her work. Also present is an exhibition file documenting an exhibition of Gikow's paintings memorializing the Kent State University shootings. Printed material is comprised of exhibition announcements and catalogs, news and magazine clippings, advertisements and brochures that Gikow illustrated, along with a book Gikow illustrated titled History of Jews in America. Of note is a published book on Gikow's work entitled Gikow by Matthew Josephson. Photographic material contains photographs of Gikow, her husband Jack Levine, her studio, other artists, including Chaim Gross, Jacob Lawrence, and Raphael Soyer, and her works of art.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection and material lent for microfilming are available on 35mm microfilm reels D230 (frames 692-1388), and reels 4874-4875 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Biographical / Historical
Ruth Gikow (1915-1932) was a New York based painter, illustrator, and serigrapher. Gikow was born in Ukraine, emigrating to New York City with her parents in 1920. She studied under John Steuart Curry at the Cooper Union Art School from 1932-1935. She also studied with Louis Ross, Louis Schanker and Raphael Soyer. In 1935 Gikow became a Works Progress Administration artist, and in 1939 Gikow was awarded a commission to paint a mural titled Children's Indoor and Outdoor Activities for the children's wing of Bronx Hospital. Her other mural work included a live demonstration at the 1943 New York City World's Fair, and commercial murals for department stores across the city. Her career also involved illustrating books such as an edition of Crime and Punishment and History of the Jews in America by Deborah Pessin; and co-founding the American Serigraph Society in which she developed her technique with silk screen printing. In 1946 Gikow married painter Jack Levine.
Her paintings are in the collection of several art museums including the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Whitney, the Museum of Modern Art, and the National Institute of Arts and Letters in New York, the Smithsonian Institute in Washington D.C., the Philadelphia Museum of Art, as well as collections at Brandeis University, and New York University.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Material on D230 was lent by Gikow in 1965. Gikow and her husband Jack Levine donated the remainder in 1978 and 1983, which was microfilmed in 1994 with grants from the Henry and Lucy Moses Fund, the Lucius N. Littauer Foundation, the Samuel Bronfman Foundation, and the Louis and Anne Abrons Foundation. After microfilming, an addition to the collection was donated by Levine in May 1999. Papers of Jack Levine donated at the same time have been cataloged separately.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as six series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1933-1972 (5 Folders: Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1949-1981 (0.5 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1950-1980 (0.2 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 4: Personal Business, circa 1954-1980 (5 Folders: Box 1)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1933-1982 (0.6 Linear feet: Box 1-2)
Series 6: Photographic Material, circa 1939-1975 (0.4 Linear feet: Box 2)
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Muralists -- New York (State) -- New York; Illustrators -- New York (State) -- New York; Serigraphers -- New York (State) -- New York; Printmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Painting, Modern -- 20th century -- New York (State) -- New York; Social realism; Jewish artists; Women artists; Women painters; Women printmakers; Artists' studios -- Photographs; Interviews; Sound recordings
- Biographical Material, 1933-1972; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 5 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material contains resumes, seven of Gikow's passports, her college yearbook from Cooper Union, a transcript from a Jewish Home Show radio interview and an audio recorded interview with Gikow done by Karl E. Fortess. Accompanying the audio tape interview is a letter from Fortress regarding the sending of the tape.
  - Passports, 1947-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Resumes and Biographical Note, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jewish Home Show Interview Transcript, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Karl E. Fortess Interview of Gikow, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key; Includes 1 sound tape reel (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cooper Union Women's Art School Yearbook, 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1949-1981; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is a mix of personal and professional letters with critics and galleries, universities, colleagues and family including Gikow's daughter Susanna Fisher Levine. Also found in this series is an address book. Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - Ruth Gikow Correspondence, 1949-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ruth Gikow Correspondence, 1965-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ruth Gikow Correspondence, 1970-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ruth Gikow Correspondence, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ruth Gikow Correspondence, 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ruth Gikow Correspondence, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ruth Gikow Correspondence, circa 1949-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Address Book, circa 1949-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Writings, circa 1950-1980; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  The writings series contains essays by Gikow on her life as an artist and as an artist's wife and reflections on art and artists more broadly. Other writings include an annotated appointment calander, lists of her artwork and miscellaneous notes.
  - Annotated Appointment Calendar, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Writings on Art and Process, circa 1950-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Autobiographical Creative Essays, circa 1950-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Autobiographical Creative Essays, Typescripts, circa 1950-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cowboys and Oracles Essay, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lists of Artwork, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1963-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Personal Business, circa 1954-1980; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 5 Folders Box 1
  Personal business document's Gikow's career through sale records and price lists, as well as receipts and correspondence related to the production of a catalog of her work. Also present is an exhibition file documenting an exhibition of Gikow's paintings memorializing the Kent State University shootings.
  - Kent State Memorial Exhibition, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Sales and Consignment Records, circa 1954-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Price Lists, circa 1961-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Book Publishing, 1969-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, circa 1968-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Printed Material, circa 1933-1982; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Printed material is comprised of news and magazine clippings, advertisements and brochures that Gikow illustrated, along with a book Gikow illustrated titled History of Jews in America; exhibition announcements and catalogs. Of note is a published book on Gikow's work entitled Gikow and associated promotional printed material.
  - Clippings, circa 1947-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Advertisement Illustrations, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cover Illustrated Programs, 1961; 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1946-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Exhibition Announcement, Jacqueline Gikow, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1940-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1953-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1960-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1965-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1972-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - History of the Jews, Book by Deborah Pessin, Illustrated by Gikow, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Gikow, Book by Matthew Josephson, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Reproductions of Artwork from Gikow Book, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Gikow Book Promotion, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Reproductions of Sketches, circa 1950-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1933-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
- Photographic Material, circa 1939-1975; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 2
  Photographic material contains photographs of Gikow, her husband Jack Levine, her studio, other artists, including Chaim Gross, Jacob Lawrence, and Raphael Soyer, along with works of art.
  - Photographs of Gikow, circa 1950-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Gikow's Studio, circa 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Jack Levine, circa 1950-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Photographs of Friends, circa 1950-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Photographs of Gikow's Murals, circa 1939-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Photographs of Gikow Artwork From Kennedy Gallery Collection, circa 1950-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, circa 1950-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24-31)